<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>riddler on Robert Hickman</title>
    <link>/tags/riddler/</link>
    <description>Recent content in riddler on Robert Hickman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/riddler/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Slicing the onion 3 ways- Toy problems in R, python, and Julia</title>
      <link>/post/riddler_nba_tour_de_frace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/riddler_nba_tour_de_frace/</guid>
      <description>Between writing up my thesis, applying to jobs hire me! I’m quite good at programming, and the ongoing pandemic, I don’t really have time to write full blogposts. I have however decided to brush up my python skills and dive headfirst into Julia. As such, I like to answer the toy problems posted at fivethirtyeight’s riddler weekly. These will likely be even a few weeks late but it motivates me to tend to the blog and keep up my programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Riddler - June 26th</title>
      <link>/post/riddler_june_26th/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/riddler_june_26th/</guid>
      <description>#for working with polygonslibrary(sf)library(sfheaders)library(tidyverse)library(gtools)set.seed(22081992)Riddler ExpressThis weeks express deals with an erratic driver:
In Riddler City, the city streets follow a grid layout, running north-south and east-west. You’re driving north when you decide to play a little game. Every time you reach an intersection, you randomly turn left or right, each with a 50 percent chance.
After driving through 10 intersections, what is the probability that you are still driving north?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Riddler 1st February 2019</title>
      <link>/post/riddler-1st-feb-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/riddler-1st-feb-2019/</guid>
      <description>Riddler ClassicIn my spare time I enjoy solving 538’s The Riddler column. This week I had a spare few hours waiting for the Superbowl to start and decided to code up a solution to the latest problem to keep me busy.
The question revolves around a card game in which whatever choice a player makes, they are likely to lose to a con artist. Formally this is phrased as:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
