<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fivemintrivia on Robert Hickman</title>
    <link>/tags/fivemintrivia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in fivemintrivia on Robert Hickman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/fivemintrivia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Five Minute Football Trivia - Trans-Europe Express</title>
      <link>/post/five_min_trivia_kraftwerk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/five_min_trivia_kraftwerk/</guid>
      <description>generally as I have less and less time to waste on meaningless football stats I get halfway through a post and abandon it. To remedy this, I want to start pushing out posts that give a reasonable half-guess at an answer within an hour or so without needing to really check my working or write good prose. This is the third of these
For this weeks question, I’m stealing straight from the source of most of my posts, The Knowledge column at The Guardian:What is the shortest total distance a club has had to travel in a Champions League winning campaign?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Minute Football Trivia - Birthday Five-A-Side</title>
      <link>/post/five_min_trivia_birthdays/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/five_min_trivia_birthdays/</guid>
      <description>generally as I have less and less time to waste on meaningless football stats I get halfway through a post and abandon it. To remedy this, I want to start pushing out posts that give a reasonable half-guess at an answer within an hour or so without needing to really check my working or write good prose. This is the second of these
A semi-common question I’ve come across when doing stupid football trivia is ‘Which Birthday could field the best 5-a-side team?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Minute Football Trivia - Invincibles</title>
      <link>/post/five_min_trivia_invincibles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/five_min_trivia_invincibles/</guid>
      <description>generally as I have less and less time to waste on meaningless football stats I get halfway through a post and abandon it. To remedy this, I want to start pushing out posts that give a reasonable half-guess at an answer within an hour or so without needing to really check my working or write good prose. This is the first of these
Liverpool Football Club have had a pretty impressive season until recently, winning 26 of the first 27 games and remaining unbeaten.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
