<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>package on Robert Hickman</title>
    <link>/tags/package/</link>
    <description>Recent content in package on Robert Hickman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/package/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>sf.chlorodot mini-package</title>
      <link>/post/sf.schlorodot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sf.schlorodot/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I’d seen two tweets with stunning examples of maps by Paul Campbell here and (taken inspiration from the first) by Imer Muhović here.
The basic idea of the dot chloropleths is to visualise not only the location clustering of each variable but the number of observations (something traditional ‘filled’ chloropleths don’t do). More importantly than this, the maps also just look really really cool.
I had a spare few minutes during work on Friday which I tidied up into a package to calculate the random position of dots for such maps which can be found on my github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Riddler 27th April 2018</title>
      <link>/post/riddler-27th-april-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/riddler-27th-april-2018/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been looking for small programming problems to practice on while running experiments. One such source is Fivethirtyeight’s Riddler column which posts conundrums weekly. This week one problem focus on one of life’s universal problems: how many urinals are needed in any bathroom for all patrons to use it without awkwardness.
Formally this is phrased as:
Some number, N, of people need to pee, and there is some number, M, of urinals in a row in a men’s room.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
