<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>maps on Robert Hickman</title>
    <link>/tags/maps/</link>
    <description>Recent content in maps on Robert Hickman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/maps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Which English County Has Won the Most Points</title>
      <link>/post/counties_league_points/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/counties_league_points/</guid>
      <description>Every so often a question on The Guardian’s The Knowledge football trivia section piques my interest and is amenable to analysis using R. Previously, I looked at club name suffixes and young World Cup winners last August. This week (give or take), a question posed on twitter caught my attention:
@TheKnowledge_GU was just chatting to some colleagues in the kitchen at work about why Essex doesn&#39;t have many big football clubs and it got me thinking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning a Pub Crawl Using R</title>
      <link>/post/cambridge_pub_crawl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cambridge_pub_crawl/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago I went on the first pub crawl I’d been on in years around my city of Cambridge. Around the same time I had also been visiting 4 very good pubs within ~200m of each other tucked away in a quiet neighbourhood of the town. Together, I wondered if it was possible with freely avaiable data to plan an optimal pub crawl around any town/area of the UK, and also, if it would be feasbile to visit every pub within the city in a single day if travelling optimally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Learned To Stop Worrying and Love Heatmaps</title>
      <link>/post/getis-ord-heatmaps-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getis-ord-heatmaps-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Whilst getting some work done browsing twitter at work today, I came across this tweet from the always excellent John Burn-Murdoch on the scourge of heatmaps. What’s most frustrating about these maps is that ggplot2 (which is underrated as mapping software, especially when combined with packages like sf in R) makes it super easy to create this bland, uninformative maps.
For instance, lets load some mapping libraries
library(tidyverse)library(sf)library(rgdal)For this blog I’m going to use data of bus stops in London, because there’s an absolute ton of them and because I love the London Datastore and it was the first public, heavy, point data file I came across.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>sf.chlorodot mini-package</title>
      <link>/post/sf.schlorodot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sf.schlorodot/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I’d seen two tweets with stunning examples of maps by Paul Campbell here and (taken inspiration from the first) by Imer Muhović here.
The basic idea of the dot chloropleths is to visualise not only the location clustering of each variable but the number of observations (something traditional ‘filled’ chloropleths don’t do). More importantly than this, the maps also just look really really cool.
I had a spare few minutes during work on Friday which I tidied up into a package to calculate the random position of dots for such maps which can be found on my github.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
